<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: s3 | Tommy Back]]></title>
  <link href="http://murrekatt.github.com/blog/categories/s3/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://murrekatt.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-08T12:20:27+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://murrekatt.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tommy Back]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Offloading Static Content for Your Web Service]]></title>
    <link href="http://murrekatt.github.com/blog/2015/09/08/offloading-static-content-for-your-web-service/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-08T11:21:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://murrekatt.github.com/blog/2015/09/08/offloading-static-content-for-your-web-service</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For web services with lot of static content that is user generated or user-
consumed content like for instance sound or video, it would normally be sent to
the backend and thus processed there. This means you need to pay bandwidth and
processing of that data. It does not matter if you are hosted on a PaaS or run
your own server infrastructure, you still need to pay to processthe data. You
alos need to deal with scaling the delivery (see Content Delivery Networks).</p>

<p>Unless you really need to get the data to your service endpoint there is a much
better way to offload this and that is to use Amazon S3 or something similar
like Google Blob Store. These can function like a CDN and can scale globally
across datacenters and continents as needed by your service.</p>

<p>Depending on the situation, e.g. if the web service is a public internet
service, a company-internal service or who generates the content, who consumes
it and how is it shared one would set up the overall system slightly different.</p>

<p>For internet services, the use case is many times that users generate content
and upload that as part of the service for themselves, for sharing or both. The
content can be private, shared or public depending on. Let’s now look at the
situation with a public internet service like Youtube where you manage videos
that users upload.</p>

<h2>Use Case</h2>

<p>In a scenario like Youtube where you have a site where users can publicly
search, play and share videos you basically want a storage that is readable by
anyone and writable as the service allows. Here read means search and download,
and, writable means create. Direct deletion of files should not be allowed as
this is not expensive in terms of bandwidth or processing and the system might
still want to keep the contents and just mark it not available.</p>

<h3>Overview</h3>

<p>What we want to set up is a AWS S3 bucket with public read and nothing else.
I.e. anyone can download given a URL that points of an object in the bucket.
Then we want to let the owner of the bucket, i.e. the controlling service
hand out permissions to upload as users want to add new videos to the service.
This means the service is aware of uploads and can control them.</p>

<p>The permissions are essentially signed URLs or policies that describe what is
allowed. E.g. user A is allowed to upload a file with a specific key
(destination in the bucket), file size and within the next hour. After that
the permission is no longer valid.</p>

<p>Let’s see how to set this up with AWS S3.</p>

<h3>Bucket</h3>

<p>The bucket needs to be set up with public read and nothing else. This is best
done with a bucket policy like so:</p>

<pre><code>{
  "Version": "2012-10-17",
  "Id": "Policy1234567890",
  "Statement": [{
    "Sid": "Stmt1234567890",
    "Effect": "Allow",
    "Principal": {
      "AWS": "*"
    },
    "Action": "s3:GetObject",
    "Resource": "arn:aws:s3:::bucketnamehere/*"
  }]
}
</code></pre>

<p>No other permissions should be per default except for the owner (Me) there is a
ACL (Access Control List) that gives all rights. Those rights are later given
on a case by case basis to users that want to upload content.</p>

<p>Let’s look at how to give permissions.</p>

<h3>Pre-signed URLs</h3>

<p>The simplest way to give permission to upload is to generate a pre-signed URL to
be used with an HTTP PUT method. This means all necessary permission information
is part of the URL as parameters.</p>

<p>Please note that browsers do not support HTTP PUT so one must either do it with
Javascript or do the second option which is HTTP POST.</p>

<p>One can set an expiration when this URL no longer is valid.</p>

<p>With this method it is not possible to restrict e.g. the file size or
automatically know if the request was successful. This is possible with the
second option pre-signed POST.</p>

<h3>Pre-signed POST</h3>

<p>The second option that also supports browsers is to do an HTTP POST with some
pre-signed content that AWS S3 can verify to allow the upload. This option is
more advanced than a pre-signed URL and it is possible to control things much
more with this. It is also more complicated as it is a HTML form sent as a
multipart HTTP request.</p>

<p>The essence of this is that the owner (or someone with the right credentials)
generate a policy that exactly describe what is allowed and signs it so that
AWS S3 can verify that the HTTP POST is valid when it arrives.</p>

<p>Both expiration and file size limits are possible to set up with the policy [5].</p>

<p>One can also set up an HTTP redirect when something is successfully uploaded
with the given permissions. This is of course useful to close the loop not
knowing if someone actually uploaded what was intended and possibly leaving
dangling ends in the service.</p>

<h2>Summary</h2>

<p>Today there are several good option how to offload user content to ease the
workload on your endpoint. Options like Amazon S3 and Google Blob Store are
very good options. The essensce is to have a storage that is scalable and
restricted to what you need and then hand out permissions for read or write
as needed by the users of your platform. This allows you to focus on building
a great service and letting someone else deal with storing and delivering
static content to your users, globally.</p>

<h2>References</h2>

<ul>
<li>[1] <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/API/sigv4-post-example.html">Example Browser-based POST.</a></li>
<li>[2] <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/API/sigv4-authentication-HTTPPOST.html">Authenticating requests in browser-based uploads using POST.</a></li>
<li>[3] <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/HTTPPOSTForms.html">HTML Forms</a></li>
<li>[4] <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/dev/PresignedUrlUploadObject.html">Pre-Signed URL.</a></li>
<li>[5] <a href="http://docs.aws.amazon.com/AmazonS3/latest/API/sigv4-HTTPPOSTConstructPolicy.html">Creating a POST policy.</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
