<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: open-source | Tommy Back]]></title>
  <link href="http://murrekatt.github.com/blog/categories/open-source/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://murrekatt.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-05-12T19:30:34+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://murrekatt.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Tommy Back]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Git Workflow Overview]]></title>
    <link href="http://murrekatt.github.com/blog/2014/10/24/git-workflow-overview/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-24T07:43:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://murrekatt.github.com/blog/2014/10/24/git-workflow-overview</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Short overview of the most important git commands and workflows. This is mainly
focused on projects on Github.</p>

<h2>Forking, Cloning and Remotes</h2>

<p>Git allows you to work in several different ways. Two good ways to work are
direct push and pull requests. The former is often used when you are alone
or when you work on your own repo (which can be either a fork or not). The
latter is usually the way to work in an open-source project so that people
send pull requests for changes from their own forks of some repo.</p>

<p>To get started, let&rsquo;s get a local repo by cloning say your fork of another
repo you&rsquo;d like to contribute to.</p>

<pre><code>git clone &lt;repo_url&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>After this you have a local repo and a remote repo on Github. The repo repo
is called <code>origin</code>. This is where you push changes.</p>

<p>If you forked an upstream repo, you should also add a remote <code>upstream</code> so
that you can easily fetch and rebase.</p>

<pre><code>git remote add upstream &lt;upstream_repo_url&gt;
git fetch upstream
</code></pre>

<p>If you collaborate with others it might as well be good to add their repos
as remotes too so that you can grab changes from there and rebase on top of
changes not yet upstream.</p>

<h2>Making Changes</h2>

<p>Changes to the code base should be done in clear and well described steps
that are put into separate commits. I.e. a larger change will consist of a
number of commits describing various parts on the way towards the change is
completed.</p>

<p>A good workflow is to create a separate branch for some changes you&rsquo;re making.
This way you can easily work on multiple things in parallel and have good
isolation between things. To create a new branch you start from a commit hash
you want to use as the starting-point (usually this is HEAD of master).</p>

<pre><code>git checkout -b some_descriptive_name
</code></pre>

<p>Now you&rsquo;re in <code>some_descriptive_name</code> and it&rsquo;s identical to where you where
when you issued the checkout-branch command.</p>

<p>Now, let&rsquo;s say you edited a files <code>Example.cpp</code> and <code>Example.hpp</code> adding a new
function <code>get_number()</code>. Now you want to add the change into a commit and
this is done by adding the files like this:</p>

<pre><code>git add Example.cpp Example.hpp
</code></pre>

<p>After this add the change into a commit:</p>

<pre><code>git commit -m 'Added function get_number() into Example.'
</code></pre>

<p>This procedure is repeated for a collection of changes (commits) until you&rsquo;re
ready to send a pull request. Before you can send a pull request you need to
push your changes to your remote repo called <code>origin</code>:</p>

<pre><code>git push origin &lt;branch_name&gt;
</code></pre>

<h2>Creating a Pull Request</h2>

<p>When you have a set of changes that you&rsquo;d like to send upstream you do that by
sending a pull request. This means that you submit your branch and the included
changes to the upstream repo so that a maintainer can merge it.</p>

<p>Sending a pull request is done on Github from your own fork. Select the branch
you are on and then click create pull request.</p>

<p>Once this is created it will go through review by whoever is a maintainer of the
upstream repo.</p>

<h2>Rebasing a Pull Request</h2>

<p>One way of working is to rebase every pull request before it gets merged. This
results in a clean commit history. When this is the process, you&rsquo;ll need to
fetch any changes that were merged upstream and rebase on top of those.</p>

<pre><code>git fetch upstream
git rebase upstream/&lt;branch&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This will catch up the current branch you are in with all changes upstream that
you fetched and then replay your local changes on top of that. If you want you
can automatically change pull to be fetch+rebase like this:</p>

<pre><code>git config --global branch.autosetuprebase always
</code></pre>

<p>and then retroactively add it to existing branches like this:</p>

<pre><code>git config branch.&lt;branch_name&gt;.rebase true
</code></pre>

<p>To update your pending pull request you need to update <code>origin</code> with your
rebased branch. To do this you need to force push</p>

<pre><code>git push +HEAD:&lt;branch&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>This will automatically update the pending pull request on Github to include
your updated commits.</p>

<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> force push rewrites history of your <code>origin</code> so be very careful with
using it to not lose commits.</p>

<h2>Resolving Conflicts when Rebasing</h2>

<p>Sometimes when you rebase there are changes that conflict with yours and then
git will stop and prompt you to make a choice what to do. In many cases there
is an automatic merge, but if this fails you need to resolve the conflicts
manually.</p>

<p>To do this you can start by looking at the files that have conflicts:</p>

<pre><code>git status
</code></pre>

<p>This lists files that you need to update. I.e. one by one you open the files
and look for e.g. HEAD to see where there&rsquo;s something you need to address. When
you have made the updates you need to add the files and continue with the
rebase like this:</p>

<pre><code>git add FileThatHadConflict.cpp
git rebase --continue
</code></pre>

<p>You might need to do this procedure multiple times depending on the conflicts
and number of commits you have etc.</p>

<h2>Interactive Rebase and Amending a Commit</h2>

<p>During review of your pull request there might be things that need to be
changed in a commit. There are two ways of dealing with this:</p>

<ul>
<li>add a new commit to change things.</li>
<li>amend an existing commit.</li>
</ul>


<p>The second option is cleaner, so let&rsquo;s look at this.</p>

<p>First you&rsquo;ll need to fetch latest upstream and rebase on that.</p>

<pre><code>git fetch upstream
git rebase upstream/&lt;branch&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Then you need to do an interactive rebase so that you can mark the commits
you want to edit so that you can make changes directlyinto those.</p>

<pre><code>git rebase -i upstream/&lt;branch&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>To edit change <code>pick</code> to <code>e</code> for one or more commits. Save and exit. Git will
replay and stop at the marked commits so that you can make changes. So just
make the change and then amend and continue rebase like this:</p>

<pre><code>git add FileThatWasAmended.cpp
git commit --amend
# save commit info
git rebase --continue
</code></pre>

<p>Once you have done all you&rsquo;re ready to force push the changes to your pull
request.</p>

<pre><code>git push origin +HEAD:&lt;branch&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>If you for some reason what to abort the rebase you can do:</p>

<pre><code>git rebase --abort
</code></pre>

<h2>Rebasing On Top of Another Branch</h2>

<p>When you&rsquo;re collaborating with others it might many times be good to share
code before it hits upstream. This is easily done with git because upstream
is just like any other repo. For convenience, add a remote to the repo you
want to collaborate with like this:</p>

<pre><code>git remote add foo &lt;foo_repo_url&gt;
git fetch foo
</code></pre>

<p>Now you can see foo&rsquo;s branches with:</p>

<pre><code>git branch -v
</code></pre>

<p>And getting code from someone is as easy as fetching and rebasing on top of
upstream:</p>

<pre><code>git rebase foo/some_branch
</code></pre>

<p>The same is true for pull requests. You can send pull requests between forks
in Github too.</p>

<h2>Some Other Useful Commands</h2>

<p>To force HEAD to something in case of some major mistake you can do:</p>

<pre><code>git reset --hard &lt;commit_hash&gt;
</code></pre>

<p><strong>NOTE:</strong> be very careful with this command so you don&rsquo;t lose anything.</p>

<h2>Useful Links</h2>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/edx/edx-platform/wiki/How-to-Rebase-a-Pull-Request">How To Rebase a Pull Request</a></li>
<li><a href="http://mark-dot-net.blogspot.ch/2012/02/to-rebase-or-not-to-rebase-that-is.html">Rebase vs. Merge</a></li>
<li><a href="http://codeinthehole.com/writing/pull-requests-and-other-good-practices-for-teams-using-github/">Pull Requests and Other Good Practices</a></li>
<li><a href="http://sarah.thesharps.us/2014/09/01/the-gentle-art-of-patch-review/">Three Phase Review Process</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
